<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A iournall of the voyage of the young Prince Fredericke Henry, Prince of Bohemia Taken in the sixt yeare of his age, from Prague in Bohemia, to Luerden in Friesland, to the court of Count Ernestus Cassimerus van Nassaw Gouernor of Friesland. With his seuerall gifts and entertainments: and the description of diuers of the chiefe cities. Being accompanyed in his passage by these of the Germane nobilitie, and others, viz. Count Attemberg. Count Henry van Nassaw. Count Stulsberg. Baron Scoske, a Bohemian lord. Mr. Iohn Ashburnham esquire, an Englishman, and gouernor to the prince. Mr. Fredericke Porvel a German, the princes tutor. With diuers other gentlemen of qualitie, seruants and other attendants.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11366</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854620</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854620</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20047</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20047)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 957:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A iournall of the voyage of the young Prince Fredericke Henry, Prince of Bohemia Taken in the sixt yeare of his age, from Prague in Bohemia, to Luerden in Friesland, to the court of Count Ernestus Cassimerus van Nassaw Gouernor of Friesland. With his seuerall gifts and entertainments: and the description of diuers of the chiefe cities. Being accompanyed in his passage by these of the Germane nobilitie, and others, viz. Count Attemberg. Count Henry van Nassaw. Count Stulsberg. Baron Scoske, a Bohemian lord. Mr. Iohn Ashburnham esquire, an Englishman, and gouernor to the prince. Mr. Fredericke Porvel a German, the princes tutor. With diuers other gentlemen of qualitie, seruants and other attendants.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By G. Eld] for Nathaniel Butter and Nicholas Bourne,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick Henry, --  Prince of Bohemia, 1614-1629.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20047:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A IOVRNALL OF THE VOYAGE of the young Prince <hi>Fredericke Henry,</hi> Prince of <hi>Bohemia:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Taken in the ſixt yeare of his age, from <hi>Prague</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> to <hi>Luerden</hi> in <hi>Frieſland,</hi> to the Court of Count <hi>Erneſtus Caſsimerus van Naſſaw</hi> Gouernor of <hi>Frieſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With his ſeuerall Gifts and Entertainments: and the deſcription of diuers of the chiefe Cities.</p>
            <p>Being accompanyed in his paſſage by theſe of the Germane Nobilitie, and others, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Count Attemberg.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Count Henry van Naſſaw.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Count Stulsberg.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Baron Scoske,</hi> a Bohemian Lord.</item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Aſhburnham Eſquire,</hi> an Engliſhman, and Gouernor to the Prince.</item>
                  <item>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Fredericke Porvel</hi> a German, the Princes Tutor.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>With diuers other Gentlemen of Qualitie, Seruants and other Attendants.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter</hi> and <hi>Nicholas Bourne.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20047:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20047:2"/>
            <head>A IOVRNALL OF the Voyage of the young Prince <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke Henry,</hi> Prince of Bohemia, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N the 12. day of September <hi>Anno</hi> 1620. the Court remoued from <hi>Prague</hi> to <hi>Brandis</hi> or <hi>Prandis,</hi> (being three miles diſtant) on the riuer <hi>Elb,</hi> neere where the riuer <hi>Gitzera</hi> fals into the <hi>Elb:</hi> where the Prince the next day following, taking his leaue of the King and Queen his father and mother, and being royally attended, ſet forwards towards <hi>Barlene,</hi> the chiefe reſidence of the Marqueſſe Elector of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> his vncle. Although the paſſages were too full of ſouldiers for him to goe the neereſt way: for which cauſe, and for the better commodity of lodging, ſhaping his courſe from <hi>Prage</hi> full North; on the thirteenth of September hee ſet out from <hi>Brandis:</hi> which Towne being no great State, is in the ſame longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and latitude with <hi>Prage,</hi> that is, 29. and 46. and ſome odde minutes, and vpon the great and faire riuer of <hi>Elbe</hi> or <hi>Albis,</hi> which the Bohemians call <hi>Labe;</hi> which we paſſing, came the ſame day to <hi>Wieſwaſſer,</hi> which ſignifies in Engliſh White wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the Bohemians call it <hi>Biela:</hi> an ancient City it is, and though it be ſituated in the Kingdome of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20047:3"/> 
               <hi>Bohemia,</hi> yet is this with diuers others vnder a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular gouernment of ſome of the ancient Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of that Country: this City is fiue miles from <hi>Brandis,</hi> eight from <hi>Prage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereabouts are alſo (almoſt) continuall great waldts or woods, which marching from the banks almoſt of the riuer <hi>Elbe,</hi> Eaſt and Weſt, tend euen to the borders of the vpper <hi>Luſatia,</hi> which is one of the incorporated Prouinces belonging to the Kingdome of <hi>Bohemia:</hi> At this <hi>Wiſwaſſer</hi> the Prince was met by the Inhabitants, and brought into the Caſtle, and there by the Burgraues appointment (himſelfe being through ſickneſſe vnable to come to waite vpon the Prince) hee was for that night entertained by the Citizens with very good ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruance.</p>
            <p>The next morning being the 14. of September, the Citizens brought him on his way with an able Conuoy of 150. horſe and foot, till hee paſt out of <hi>Bohemia</hi> into <hi>Leutznatz</hi> or <hi>Luſatia;</hi> where at his firſt entrance the townſmen of <hi>Gabel</hi> met him, the chiefe of which company in the name of the townſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men made a complementall Oration, intimating their faithfull loues, and his moſt hearty welcome vnto them. The Oration being ended, hee was conducted by them towards <hi>Gabel.</hi> Within halfe a miles riding he was met by a troope of horſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing about 150. which were ſent from the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iegerenſdorf.</hi> Here the Conuoy of <hi>Wiſwaſſer</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned backe, and this troope brought him to the towne of <hi>Gabel,</hi> here the Prince dined. This <hi>Gabel</hi> is one of the firſt good townes on the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20047:3"/> of <hi>Luſatia</hi> towards <hi>Bohemia;</hi> it ſtands neere vnto the riuer of <hi>Nieſſe</hi> one of the chiefe Floods of <hi>Luſatia,</hi> which riſes not farre from hence.</p>
            <p>From hence departing after dinner, about a mile off from the Towne, he was met by a ſecond troupe of horſe, ſent alſo from the ſaid Marqueſſe of <hi>Iegerenſdorf,</hi> by which troupes his Highneſſe was conuoyed to the City of <hi>Zittaw</hi> or <hi>Sittaw,</hi> ſtanding vpon the riuer of <hi>Nieſſe.</hi> At the entrance whereof, he was receiued by two other troopes of horſe, and three companies of foot, beſides the Citizens themſelues ſtanding all in their Armes on each ſide, with muſicke of Trumpets on the Cathedrall Church, and Haultboyes on the tower of the Statehouſe, which ſounded vntill the Prince was entred into his lodging. Before which, by commandement of the towne, was placed a ſtrong Guard of both horſe and foot, beſides two compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of foot placed within the gates in the Court, for defence of his perſon. And at each gate of the City for that night was ſet an extraordinary ſtrong Court of Guard both of horſe and foot, the times being then dangerous, becauſe the Duke of <hi>Saxo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> was then in Armes, and held his Leaguer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the City of <hi>Baultzen,</hi> within foure miles to the North-Weſt of that place, vpon the riuer of <hi>Spre;</hi> and we were now vpon the borders of <hi>Meiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen,</hi> which is one of the Duke of <hi>Saxonies</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, and confines vpon <hi>Luſatia,</hi> by a long tract of ground. And thus farre euen from <hi>Prage</hi> in <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> vnto <hi>Zittaw</hi> in <hi>Luſatia,</hi> our Court was full North.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20047:4"/>
            <p>But the next day being the 15. of September, departing from thence, we tooke vp vpon the right hand more towards the Eaſt, ſetting forward to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Gorlitz,</hi> which alſo ſtands vpon the riuer of <hi>Nieſſ</hi> aforeſaid, which riuer riſing in the Country of <hi>Mieſſen</hi> (I take it) eaſt-ward of <hi>Gabel,</hi> paſſeth by <hi>Zittaw, Gorlitz,</hi> and ſo north-ward through both the <hi>Luſatiaes,</hi> till it fals into the <hi>Oder,</hi> which parts <hi>Luſatia</hi> from <hi>Sileſia.</hi> On the way towards this <hi>Gor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litz,</hi> (the Princes horſes being almoſt wearied) he was met by certaine Coaches and diuers troopes of horſe, ſent from the Marqueſſe of <hi>Iegerenſdorf,</hi> who in that time of warre had his chiefe reſidence in that City. This guard tooke vp both ſides of the way for a mile and a halfe together: and within halfe a mile off the City, the Marqueſſe himſelfe in perſon met the Prince, accompanied with 4000 horſe and foote. And within a quarter of a mile off the City, he was receiued by the Citizens, ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging themſelues in armour on both ſides the way, their order extending euen to the very entrance of the Marqueſſe his Palace. For the Princes better contentment, the ſouldiers were all commanded to march by in Battaglia and warlike order, with Drummes, Fifes, and Enſignes diſplayed. After all which the Prince was by the Marqueſſe and all his Councell moſt royally feaſted. He was lodged in the Palace in a moſt faire chamber, richly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, and cut with antique works of great art and beauty. At this good entertainment we ſtayed two nights and two dayes.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Gorlitz</hi> is the chiefe towne of the vpper
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20047:4"/> 
               <hi>Luſatia,</hi> and a fayre and a ſtrong one it is, as being naturally defended, partly by his mountainous ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, and by the nearneſſe of the Riuer of <hi>Neiſs,</hi> ouer which it hath a commodious &amp; well couered wooden Bridge. The Church of S. <hi>Peters</hi> is a very fayre peece, as is alſo the Tower of the State-houſe.</p>
            <p>On the third day after being the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> the Marqueſſe with all his traine and troopes, brought his Highnes halfe a mile out of Towne, and there ſolemnly taking his leaue, parted with him, commanding his Troopes to goe on with the Prince, and to convoy him to a gariſon-Town of his called <hi>Lauben,</hi> which is to the Eaſt-ward of <hi>Gorlitz,</hi> and ſomething out of the way. At our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach within two miles of the town, we might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the Souldiers both Horſe and Foot drawne forth in two diuiſions, the Horſe in one, and the Foot in the other, and both ranged in battell-aray. The reaſon of this demeanour, was a iealouſie of ſome treachery which they conceiued to be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt their Gariſon, for that the night before the Princes Quarter-maſter being ſent before, to giue them intelligence of his Highnes comming, they ſuppoſed him to haue bin a ſpy, and clapt him vp cloſe priſoner, lading him with irons. Theſe troops and companies of Gariſon Souldiers being afarre off diſcouered, bred alſo the ſame iealouſie of them in vs, as our approach did of vs in them, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part hauing a miſpriſion of the others inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Whereupon it was reſolued to ſend a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet before, with certaine Gentlemen, to giue and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:20047:5"/> take ſatisfaction on eyther ſide. Whereupon they being better ſatisfied, and all miſtruſt being quite taken away, the chiefe Burgers of the Towne ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uanced forwards, and comming to the Prince, they kiſt his Highnes hand: And after ſome ſolemne Speech of entertainment, with their excuſe allea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, for their late behauiour, imputing the ſame to the danger of the time, and their vnexpected and ſodaine notice of his arriuall, the Prince mounted on horſe-backe, &amp; rode cleare through their troops towards the Towne: and hauing paſt them, the horſe and foot diſcharged three vollies of ſhot for his welcome: &amp; comming to the gates of the town he was receiued by a guard of towne-dwellers, and by them conueyed to his place of reſt, where for that day he dined, where alſo the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerenſdorfs</hi> Conuoy of horſe left vs, and returned to <hi>Gorlitz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This towne of <hi>Lauben</hi> is ſituated vpon the banks of the Riuer <hi>Queis,</hi> which alſo runnes into the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> and is neare vnto the borders of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a necke of land which thruſts out from <hi>Bohemia</hi> alſo, which being very narrow at <hi>Gabel,</hi> we touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon <hi>Mieſſen</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxonies</hi> Country.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Lauben</hi> is in the frontiers (as it were) both of <hi>Bohemia</hi> on the South-ſide, and <hi>Sileſia</hi> on the Eaſt, it ſelfe being the vtmoſt towne of the vpper <hi>Luſatia,</hi> which makes the Gariſon to ſtand more warily vpon their guard.</p>
            <p>After dinner he was conducted out of the ſame Towne by a troope of horſe of the towne gariſon, which waited vpon his Highnes, till hee came to
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20047:5"/> the Citie of <hi>Limberge</hi> in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> which town ſtands vpon the Riuer of <hi>Bober,</hi> and not farre from the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer <hi>Queis</hi> aforeſaid. But before he came neare the Citie, the Prince was met by a troope of horſe from thence, in the middeſt of whom he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiged to his lodging in the towne, which was one of the chiefe Burgers houſes, where they placed a ſtrong guard at the doore, for the ſafety of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This was vpon a Saturday at night.</p>
            <p>That day (his Highnes comming thither being knowne abroad in the country) all the young No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry thereabouts came in to ſee the Prince, and to wait vpon his Highnes at table at Supper-time, ſo that all the Princes ſeruants were for that time diſmiſſed from their attendance vpon him.</p>
            <p>The next day being Sunday, and <hi>Septemb.</hi> 19. the Prince mounted on horſe-backe, the Nobilitie go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before him on foot, and their children on each ſide, with the troops of horſe and Foot attending. In which ſtately and ſolemne manner his Highnes rode to Church, and heard a Sermon. Whence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing returned, he dined with the Nobility.</p>
            <p>After dinner the ſame day, he was by them and their troops conducted to the Citie of <hi>Somponſel,</hi> where he was moſt nobly entertayned of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens. So ſoon as the Prince was diſcouered by the Watch vpon their Towers, they ſounded their Trumpets, and beat vp their great kettle-Drums, continuing ſo vntill he came to the gates. Where as ſoone as he was entred, the Townſ-men making a guard of themſelues, gaue the Prince a luſty volley
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:20047:6"/> of ſhot for his welcome. Then with the ſound of Corners and Haultboyes he was entertained to his lodging. At the entrance whereof the Townſ-men gaue him another volley of ſhot, and placing a ſtrong court of guard for that night before his lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging, departed.</p>
            <p>The 20. of <hi>Sept.</hi> the Nobilitie tooke their leaue of the Prince, and the Townſ-men waited vpon him with a conuoy to a place called <hi>Crozan,</hi> or <hi>Croſſen,</hi> where his Highnes dined.</p>
            <p>After dinner the ſame Conuoy brought him through till hee came to a citie called <hi>Frieſtadt,</hi> which is not farre from the borders of Poland, and lyes to the North the riuer <hi>Oder,</hi> running between this part of <hi>Sileſia</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> through the Duchy of <hi>Croſſen,</hi> which is finally parted from hence by a ledge of woody mountaines, tending north-weſt and by north by a long tract to the Eaſt-ward Here the troopes of <hi>Somponſel</hi> left him, and returned homewards, the Souldiers both horſe and foote of <hi>Frieſtadt</hi> receiuing him into their rankes in warlike order. All which by reaſon it was late and darke, was done by the Citizens by torch-light: by whom hee was gallantly conducted to his lodging, where he reſted for that night.</p>
            <p>This being the laſt towne we lay at in <hi>Sileſia,</hi> the next day being the 21. of September, the Prince being conuoyed by ſome horſe of the towne, wee entred into the <hi>Brandenburgher</hi> marck, that is, the marches or borders of the land of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> through which we paſſed on to the City of <hi>Franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> vpon <hi>Oder,</hi> ſo called, to diſtinguiſh it from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:20047:6"/> the other <hi>Franckford</hi> which is neere to the Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, where the great Mart is twice a yeare kept; which is alſo called <hi>Franckford</hi> vpon <hi>Maine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that that ſtands vpon the riuer of <hi>Maine,</hi> as this doth vpon the riuer of <hi>Oder.</hi> This laſt towne being vnder the gouernment of the Marqueſſe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> the chiefe Citizens at the Princes arriuall (according to their wonted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to noble ſtrangers) preſented their loues in huge flaggons of wine (which growes here) and banquetting ſtuffe, to the Prince; their flaggons being ſo much the greater, in regard of their loues to the Ducheſſe of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> their Princeſſe, who is Aunt to the Prince. This being moreouer the generall courteſie of the great Cities of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> to preſent their loues to all Princes their friends, and Ambaſſadors of Princes, with an Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, the Burgers bring each of them a great bottle of wine, which hangs by a ringle vpon his arme; and if hee hath any buſineſſe or Embaſſie to their State, they ſend him alſo Oates and Fiſh.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Franckford</hi> is eſteemed the third towne of worth in the Country, and being vpon the very North weſt angle of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> and about ſome 14. yeares before our being there (viz. <hi>Anno</hi> 1606.) was made an Vniuerſity by <hi>Ioachim</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburg:</hi> the <hi>Oder</hi> runnes vpon the Eaſt ſide, the other parts are fenced in by the mountaines.</p>
            <p>From hence vpon the 22 of September wee ſet forwards towards <hi>Rutterſdorp,</hi> but the way being waſte ground, and without habitation, wee were faine to haue our prouiſion carried along with vs,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20047:7"/> and dined that day at a Boers houſe. The ſame night his Highneſſe came to the village of <hi>Rutterſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorp,</hi> where he lodged in the Caſtle, both which belong vnto the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this place (the Marqueſſe himſelfe being then in <hi>Pruſsia</hi> or <hi>Pruce</hi> land) the Prince was faine for that night to content himſelfe with ſuch enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment as the place could afford. But the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſſe being certified of the Prince her Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phewes being there, ſent poſt all night, with plate and other prouiſion; which made ſo good ſpeed, that by the morning there was ſtore of furniture, and by break-faſt time very good variety of proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of all ſorts; which was a ſtrange change, and a ſudden alteration, ouer night to be ſerued in veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Tin, and in the morning to haue a Cupbord of Plate. And thus by the Ducheſſe noble care, the Princes ſupper was well mended, by a full and ſufficient break-faſt.</p>
            <p>This Marchioneſſe of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> is named <hi>Elizabetha Charlotta,</hi> daughter to <hi>Fredericke</hi> the fourth Prince Elector Palatine; and ſiſter to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> the Princes father.</p>
            <p>After which the 23: of September hee ſet on towards <hi>Berlin,</hi> the Court of the Marqueſſe, and ordinary place of his reſidence. The Ducheſſe hearing of his aproach, by a Poſt which the Prince diſpatcht to her aforehand, to giue her Highneſſe notice of his being ſo nigh; the Ducheſſe ſent forth her brother Prince <hi>Lodowicke,</hi> Duke of <hi>Simmern,</hi> and vncle to the Prince, together with a young Poliſh Duke (whoſe father had beene baniſhed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20047:7"/> out of <hi>Poland</hi>) and Count <hi>Philip van Solmes,</hi> who all with a faire traine came to meet the Prince, of whom, after moſt ioyfull and mutuall ſalutations, he was brought into the Palace, where his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with the reſt of his followers were moſt nobly welcomed, and royally feaſted.</p>
            <p>This gallant young Prince, vncle to our Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> is ſtiled <hi>Lodowicke Philip,</hi> Count Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, &amp;c. was borne Nouem. 22. 1602. had the two Dukedomes of <hi>Simmern, Lautern,</hi> with the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try of <hi>Sponheim</hi> aſſigned him for his portion, by his fathers Teſtament; which was confirmed vnto him by the Emperour <hi>Rodulphus</hi> the ſecond: he going vp with his brother into <hi>Bohemia,</hi> had all his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try &amp; goods taken from him by <hi>Spinola</hi> in the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate: hee went from <hi>Prage</hi> to <hi>Berlin</hi> before Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> where they now meeting, went into the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> together.</p>
            <p>Here we abode ten dayes, hauing as great va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of entertainment, as that time of mourning would permit. For the old Marqueſſe Elector be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing lately deceaſed, and the houſhold and whole Court all in mourning, and the day of the Funerall drawing neere, was not a time of mirth or mask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In our ſtay here, this one thing was excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding well worth the ſeeing and remembring, which was this; The time of the Funerall growing, the vault in the great Church was opened, where Marqueſſes Electors of <hi>Brandenburg</hi> ſtill vſe to be enterred. The Prince and all we of his traine were brought in to ſee the place; going downe into which, there was an obiect of State Antiquity and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:20047:8"/> much reuerence, namely, the bodies of 16 Princes embaulmed in Coffins of Tin, and laid by three and three on the top of each other, with their ſwords and ſpurs hanging by them: which alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the worth of the preſent ſight, ſhowes alſo the antiquity of the ſucceſſion ſince the choice of that place of buriall. The Funerall was appointed to be fiue dayes after the Princes departure, which was now at hand.</p>
            <p>After ten dayes ſtay therefore, on the 3. of Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the Prince tooke his leaue of the Marchioneſſe Electoreſſe his Aunt, and of the reſt of the Court, and departed out of <hi>Berlin;</hi> and being accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with Prince <hi>Lodowick</hi> his Vncle, and Count <hi>Philip van Solmes,</hi> who from hence iournied with him all the way, and neuer left him till he came into <hi>Holland;</hi> they arriued the firſt night at an old City and a ſtrong Caſtle called <hi>Spandaw,</hi> for now from <hi>Berlin</hi> we turned about again on the left hand and full Weſt: the riuer of <hi>Spre</hi> vpon which <hi>Berlin</hi> is ſituated, being betwixt that City and this <hi>Spandaw.</hi> Here the Prince lodged all night, his prouiſions and entertainments being all made at the charges of the Marchioneſſe Electoreſſe. This <hi>Spandaw</hi> ſtands neere the conſcience of the two riuers <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> and <hi>Spre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day being the 4. of October, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces dined at a place called <hi>Sando,</hi> and the ſame night they lodged at a Dorpe called <hi>Berneſe;</hi> which becauſe they be places of no great account, I there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſe them ouer without any more deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:20047:8"/>
            <p>The 5. of October the Princes dyned at the Citty of <hi>Ratenaw,</hi> which ſtands by the Riuer of <hi>Hauell,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond this Citty, and to the North or Northweſt loſes himſelfe and his name in the greater <hi>Elue</hi> or <hi>Albis.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter dinner they ſet forwards againe, and came that night to the Caſtle of <hi>Tungermund</hi> on the Riuer <hi>Elue.</hi> The place is ſomething old, but what it is, is in the Marqueſſe of <hi>Brandenburgs</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 6. of October, the Princes paſſed through the Foreſt of <hi>Neſlingham,</hi> where they alſo hunted; and that night they lay at the Marqueſſes Lodge in the Forreſt: and thus farre the Marchioneſſe ſent her plate, furniture, and ſeruants to attend the Princes, and feaſted them hitherto at her own charges. Which from hence being the boundary of the Marquiſate on that ſide, returned home againe towards <hi>Berline.</hi> And all this while we held our courſe full Weſt from <hi>Berline.</hi> By the Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of this Foreſt runs the Riuer <hi>Ohre,</hi> which we paſſed.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 7. of October, they entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Brunſwick</hi> Land, and dyning at a Towne called <hi>Caluer,</hi> they came the ſame night to a Colledge of Lutherans cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Miriando:</hi> where the Rector would not open his gates to receiue the Princes, vntil he heard his Princes the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> pleaſure, who was at the ſame time 7. miles off from that place. Here we ſtayed 2. houres and aboue, in a terrible ſtorme of rayne and winde, vntill a Poſt which the Princeſſe had diſpatched the night before vnto the Duke, was returned. Vpon whoſe arryuall with Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters from the Duke, the Princeſſe were receiued with all fitting reſpects, and the beſt entertainement that the place could afford. The Rector and the Society excuſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20047:9"/> by reaſon of the times, which were dangerous, and full of ſuſpition, and the perſons of the Princes vnknown to any of them, and the Colledge it ſelfe being a place of importance. A tedious night this was and a could, and ſome were wet with the rayne, and otherſome ſcapt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. But that which gaue vs ſome comfort, was; that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout midnight there came another Poſt from the Duke, who requeſted the Princes to ſtay there all the next day alſo, for that the Duke had not made his prouiſion for their entertainement at his Court in ſuch a ſhort warning. And in the meane his Highnes ſent in his own furniture for the Princes table, and commanded ſuch prouiſion to be brought in, as the Country there abouts could afford, ſo that we had there the next day by dinner time, all things fitting for entertainement.</p>
            <p>The next day being the 9. of October, the Princes left the Colledge, and ſet on towards <hi>Wolfenbuttell,</hi> the chiefe place of reſidence of the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> &amp; where the Court then was. But a little before we came to the Citty, the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> himſelfe, with the L. Chancellor of the Duchy, diuers of the priuy Councell, with many Nobles and Gentlemen, came forth of the Towne, with many faire Companies of horſe, to entertain the 2. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; ſo went along together with them into the Town. Within which were diuers Companies of Souldiers with full Armies vnder their ſeuerall Enſignes with Colours flying, with Trumpets ſounding, Fifes playing, &amp; Drums beating in warlike manner, very gallant to behold, which ſtood along vntill wee came to the Caſtle. The Hault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyes and Cornets playing in the meane time from of the top of a Tower, and a peale of Ordinance being ſhot
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20047:9"/> off at their entrance into the Caſtle.</p>
            <p>The Princes were led into very ſtately, rich, and fayer Roomes in the Caſtle, and euery where in the houſe there Princely plenty and variety of all things neceſſary.</p>
            <p>The Princes hauing repoſed themſelues a while, were by the Duke brought into the Dutcheſſe Chamber, who being allied to them both, receiued them with all Ioy and contentment.</p>
            <p>Supper time being come, the Princes were againe brought into a wondrous faier roome, where the Tables were couered and great ſtate vſed according to the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man faſhion of entertainement, which is full and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous. In this ſupping place, there was a roome wherein there was a very large and rich Cupboard of plate; at one end of which ſtood the muſick of Inſtruments and voices, and at the other end ſtood the Officers of the Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler and Buttery, to fill wine and beer to the table. For here is beere in this Country which is rare in other places of <hi>Germany,</hi> though ſcarce good any where. Yet here at this <hi>Wolfenbuttell,</hi> is a huge vaſt Tunne, larger then that of <hi>Hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleberg,</hi> but this is filled with <hi>Brunſwick</hi> beer, as that other with Rheniſh wine. There were alſo 6. other tables, where the 2. Princes ſeruants did eate, the Dukes own Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men bearing them company, which time and the whole three daies that we ſtaied here at this Royal entertainment was ſpent with great mirth, iollity and extraordinary ſhow of magnificence, bounty, and courteſie; al which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent well became a kinſman and a Prince.</p>
            <p>The preſent Duke of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> name is, <hi>Fredericus Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricus,</hi> he was born the 5. of <hi>April</hi> 1591. he married <hi>Anna So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> daughter of <hi>Iohn Sigiſmund, Marqueſſe Elector of Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg</hi> then lately dead in <hi>Noue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber</hi> 1619, &amp; ſiſter to <hi>Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20047:10"/> Wilhelmus</hi> the preſent Prince: ſhe was borne March 17. 1598. the Dukes alliance with the Prince comes in by the mothers ſide: for <hi>Anne Queen of England</hi> was daughter to <hi>Frederick</hi> the 2. King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> as was alſo <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> her elder ſiſter, the mother of this preſent Duke. The Dutcheſſes alliance with the Prince comes in by the houſe of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> of which ſhe is deſcended. The Duke of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> hath as yet no children; his onely bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and heire apparent is our valorous noble Champion <hi>Chriſtian D. of Brunſwick,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Halberſtadt:</hi> he hath or had alſo 5. ſiſters.</p>
            <p>Leauing therefore this Citty the 14. of October in the morning, the ſame day they came to a place called <hi>Stanberge,</hi> where the Princes dyned at the Dukes char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. The ſame night they lodged at a place called <hi>Collen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge,</hi> which ſtands vpon the Weſt ſide of the Riuer of <hi>Glein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 15. day the 2. Princes dyned at <hi>Hamelen</hi> which is by the <hi>Riuer</hi> of <hi>Weſter,</hi> and on the Eaſt ſide. After dinner they went to <hi>Dalmel,</hi> where they lodged. And thus farre the Princes was feaſted and furniſhed whith Plate and other prouiſion Royall, at the ſole coſt and charges of his Highneſſe the Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> who is elder brother to Duke <hi>Chriſtian of Brunſwick,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Halberſtadt</hi> the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous young Warriour; and this Town is vpon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines of the Duchy of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> which is bounded on the Weſt by the Country of <hi>Weſtphalia,</hi> from which the <hi>Weſer</hi> parts it. Here the Dukes Seruants and Officers re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the Princes backe againe to <hi>Wolfenbuttell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Duchy of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> was ſometimes accounted to <hi>Saxony,</hi> and got a particular and diſtinct name from <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:20047:10"/> who being ſon to <hi>Ludolphus</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> laid the foundations of Citty in this Duchy, which of him is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Brunſwick;</hi> the Dutchy of <hi>Luneburg</hi> hath alſo been poſſeſſed by the Dukes of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> continuing ſo vntill the yeere of Chriſt 1430. in which the Country was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided between <hi>William the victorious,</hi> who had the title of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> and his vncle <hi>Bernard,</hi> who had the title of <hi>Luneburg:</hi> in whoſe poſterity both theſe Dukedomes ſtill remaine, the Dukes of both being both of one family, <hi>Brunſwick</hi> being of the direct line, the elder houſe, and the greater Dukedome. The chiefe City both of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> and of all <hi>Saxony,</hi> is the Towne of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> which giues name to the whole Duchy, although the Court be moſt commonly kept at <hi>Wolfenbuttell,</hi> which with the whole Duchy we hauing left behind vs, entred next into <hi>Cleueland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 16. of October ſetting out ſomewhat late, we ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryued the ſame night at a Citty called <hi>Belfield,</hi> where within a mile of the Towne, they were receiued by cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine troopes of horſe, and ſo conueyed to the Citty. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring the Gates, they were welcomed with a peale of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; and ſo by the Towneſmen in Armour, they were brought into the Caſtle of <hi>Spanberg,</hi> where the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Captaine entertained them with their forces marſhalled in warlike order. Here the Princes were fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted 4. dayes.</p>
            <p>In the meane ſpace it was conſulted vpon for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſafety; that ſeeing they were now to paſſe by diuers Garriſons of the Enemies: that it were beſt to diſpatch a Poſt before hand to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to certify his Excellency of the Princeſſes neerenes, which was alſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20047:11"/> done. Both the Armies of the States and the Spaniards being then about <hi>Weſel.</hi> Here it was alſo agreed vpon to ſend Prince <hi>Lodowick</hi> with ſome others another way into <hi>Holland;</hi> that ſo the Country-people might be ſatisfied with his preſence in ſtead of the Princes; which tooke effect accordingly; and did not onely giue the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple good content through whom he paſſed, who came flocking into the high waies to ſee him; but alſo diuerted their expectations, from any thought of his paſſage any other way: by meanes whereof, his Highnes the Prince of <hi>Bohemia</hi> paſſed in his way with the more ſafety and ſecrecy.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Spanburg</hi> Caſtle we came next to the Caſtle of <hi>Arden,</hi> which is vnder the Graue of <hi>Benthem;</hi> and ſo by <hi>Glandorpe</hi> to <hi>Mareling,</hi> where we lodged all night. From whence forward the Towns being neer &amp; ſo well known, I forbeare to make any further deſcription of them, but onely name them as we paſſe through them.</p>
            <p>From thence we went to <hi>Ruſſenbeck;</hi> from thence to <hi>Embsbourne;</hi> from thence to <hi>North-horne;</hi> from thence to <hi>Hardenberg,</hi> where we lodged. From thence we went to <hi>Realte;</hi> from thence to <hi>Deuenter</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> where we met with the Princes againe.</p>
            <p>The next day we ſet forwards towards <hi>Swoll,</hi> which is a ſtrong Town of Garriſon; where we ſtaied two nights and one day. And here the Count <hi>Erneſt</hi> van <hi>Caſsimere</hi> (who comming in Poſt from the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Leaguer at <hi>Weſel,</hi> had before met with the Princes) receiued the Prince into his charge, and ſafe protection. And here Prince <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> departed from his Highnes, &amp; went directly towards the <hi>Hage:</hi> And Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> kept on towards <hi>Freez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20047:11"/>
            <p>The next day at dinner being the 25. of October, wee came to a Citty of Garriſon called <hi>Steenwick,</hi> where his Highneſſe was met by the Burgers in Armes, &amp; receiued into the Town with a volley of ſhot, and comming to the Caſtle they diſcharged a peale of Ordinance for his welcome: and all marched by in warlike manner in the Princes view.</p>
            <p>From thence after dinner they came to <hi>Wolfingow,</hi> where they reſted all that night.</p>
            <p>The next day, they dined at <hi>Hernenfen,</hi> and came the ſame night to <hi>Luerden</hi> in <hi>Freezland,</hi> the place whether at his firſt ſetting out of <hi>Prage,</hi> it was his intention to goe. Here the chiefeſt of the Town met the Prince on Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back. At the entrance thereof, the Ordinance of the Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were diſcharged to welcome him: and the Burgers within the Town in Armes, ranking themſelues on each ſide; conueied his Highnes to the Caſtle being the Court of <hi>Count Erneſtus van Caſsimerus;</hi> at that inſtant time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing receiued in ſucceſſion of <hi>Count William of Naſſaw</hi> his brother lately deceaſed, for Gouernour of <hi>Friezland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Prince being come to the Court, and brought to an exceeding faire Chamber, beheld all the Townſmen marching by in their Armes: &amp; then being brought to the Chamber of the Counteſſe, he was there moſt Nobly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by them both, with all ioy and ſolemnity.</p>
            <p>And thus it pleaſed the Almighty God to leade this ſweet young Princes firſt one way, and then againe another way, now through friends Countries, and now through foes, as from <hi>Heidleberg</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> to <hi>Prage</hi> in <hi>Bohemia</hi> at firſt; ſo now againe from <hi>Prage</hi> to <hi>Luerden:</hi> which is almoſt round about the middle part
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20047:12"/> of <hi>Germany.</hi> A Iourney by Land which would haue tired the little <hi>Iül<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> Which two, as they may hitherto be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared together for their high birth, (both being borne of <hi>gods,</hi> and both deſcended from <hi>Venus</hi>) and their early tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels, and in the loſſe of their natiue Countries; ſo it may pleaſe God alſo to conclude them alike in this too: that it may be ſaid hereafter, how that they were both; The Fathers of a race of Emperours.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>That ſo the Townes he paſt, may for their honours ſay,</l>
               <l>Nere, Prince, King, Emperor, Frederick Henry lay.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20047:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
